<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Pondering Troth</title><link href="https://musingv.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://musingv.github.io/feeds/all.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://musingv.github.io/</id><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Resuscitating The Patriarchy?</title><link href="https://musingv.github.io/review-deyoung-patriarchy-1.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2022-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Musing Villein</name></author><id>tag:musingv.github.io,2022-08-01:/review-deyoung-patriarchy-1.html</id><summary type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Good morning. Today I’m starting a series reflecting on Kevin’s DeYoung’s article “&lt;a href="https://www.desiringgod.org/articles/death-to-the-patriarchy"&gt;Death To the Patriarchy?&lt;/a&gt;” I’m tempted to apologize for the clickbait headline, but after carefully working through his article multiple times, my  most sensible interpretation of the article concludes that Kevin is advocating for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
&lt;p&gt;Good morning. Today I’m starting a series reflecting on Kevin’s DeYoung’s article “&lt;a href="https://www.desiringgod.org/articles/death-to-the-patriarchy"&gt;Death To the Patriarchy?&lt;/a&gt;” I’m tempted to apologize for the clickbait headline, but after carefully working through his article multiple times, my  most sensible interpretation of the article concludes that Kevin is advocating for patriarchy in the broadest sense – a society that promotes male authority and female submission&lt;sup id="fnref:barr"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:barr"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My plan for this series is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand Kevin’s purpose in writing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand Kevin’s main supporting arguments and flow of thought.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Carefully respond with my most significant reactions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Share a few quick takeaways.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Offer my conclusions – will my advocacy for patriarchy increase?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having laid out that plan, I’m immediately challenged on how to answer the question: What is Kevin’s purpose in writing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="first-thought"&gt;First Thought&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I started working through the article, I thought Kevin was going to argue for using the term &lt;em&gt;complementarity&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;patriarchy&lt;/em&gt; because the term far better represents Jesus’ vision for humanity. After all, the opening seems to set up that direction:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What is the difference between patriarchy and complementarity — and which is the better term for capturing the full vision of Christian manhood and womanhood?… So what is the most accurate term for those who want to recapture a lost vision of sexual differentiation and order?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From there, the article spends quite a bit of space on the origins of the term &lt;em&gt;complementarity&lt;/em&gt; and the negative baggage surrounding the term &lt;em&gt;patriarchy&lt;/em&gt;. But this focus clearly isn’t Kevin’s goal. After all, if that was the purpose, he could have stopped far earlier:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why not end the article right here? Complementarianism is good; patriarchy is bad. Case closed. Enough said, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, there’s that curious turn of phrase “those who want to recapture a lost vision of sexual differentiation and order?” At the risk of reading too much into a few words, Kevin seems to be saying that there is a proper order which:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Previously existed (otherwise it couldn’t be recaptured).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has gender as a key component&lt;sup id="fnref:gender"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:gender"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, perhaps the primary component.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Represents the full vision of Christian manhood and womanhood.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, there’s the title – “Death to Patriarchy?” – which perhaps gives a hint that Kevin is going for more than just a terminology discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="second-take"&gt;Second Take&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the purpose is to lay out a holistic complementarian perspective. Part way through the article, Kevin writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the vision of male-female complementarity is to be more than a seemingly arbitrary commitment to men leading in the home and being pastors in the church, we cannot settle for a proper interpretation of 1 Timothy 2. Of course, careful exegesis is absolutely critical. But we need more than the right conclusions. We need to help people see that our exegetical conclusions do not just fit with the best hermeneutical principles; they fit with the way the world is and the way God made men and women.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a reader, I resonate with this goal. From what I’ve read of complementarian materials, this purpose would address an Achilles’ heel for a movement that often struggles to articulate the grand beauty of gender distinctions: The strength of complementarian materials I’ve read is their ability to lay out a compelling case from scripture; the greatest weakness is to present those beliefs as more than scattered commands from God based on a mysterious (but presumably very wise) plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So taking those commands and working them into the greater creation/redemptive narrative would be a laudable undertaking. At this point, I’m enthusiastically looking for where Kevin goes with this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="round-three"&gt;Round Three&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, I actually think Kevin’s purpose is best expressed at the end of the article when he boldly writes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The biblical vision of complementarity cannot be true without something like patriarchy also being true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is, he wants to rehabilitate and promote the concept of patriarchy, whatever it is called. He wants to help people understand that patriarchy isn’t the indefensible mess that many view it as. In fact, it is essential if one wants to hold complementary views. This purpose also explains the earlier language when Kevin asks for the best term for recapturing  “a lost vision of sexual differentiation and order.” And in case one might think I’m reading too much into his conclusion, he says the same thing midway through the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;most complementarians do not realize that in rejecting patriarchy, they have, according to the contemporary rules of the game, rejected the very reality they thought they could reclaim by an appeal to complementarity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that’s a bold and audacious goal: Agree with Kevin about patriarchy or become an egalitarian.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Am I being uncharitable to Kevin here?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t know. I’d like to think so because I’m suggesting a really unpopular stance for Kevin that I find nearly indefensible. I see Kevin’s approach as particularly challenging to defend&lt;sup id="fnref:defend"&gt;&lt;a class="footnote-ref" href="#fn:defend"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. And I want to be charitable in my interpretations and slow to frame those I disagree with as extremists. So I’d really like to be wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this interpretation of his purpose also makes sense of why the article’s argumentation focuses on establishing gender differences and defusing the sensitivities around rule and submission. The grander narrative he’s promoting is that men have authority, and women submit. Not in a narrow sense – each woman has a man she submits to (her husband) – but in a far broader sense: Across society, women submit to men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might think that when Kevin says “something like patriarchy,” he doesn’t mean patriarchy exactly. But he never offers an alternative definition of what he means. On &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/brockbahler/status/1552338014474575873"&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, someone pointed out that &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bethallisonbarr"&gt;Beth Barr&lt;/a&gt; defined patriarchy in her book, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Making-Biblical-Womanhood-Subjugation-Became/dp/1587434709"&gt;The Making of Biblical Womanhood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (pages 12-13), as having three primary meanings in the English language:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Male ecclesiastical leaders…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legal power of male household heads (fathers/husbands)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A society that promotes male authority and female submission&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I find that definition seems pretty reasonable. It even avoids the loaded terms that Kevin expresses concern about – dominance, oppression, repression, inferiority, and subservience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I clearly see Kevin writing about far more than ecclesiastical leadership. Or the legal authority of household heads. And everything he writes fits really well into the third definition - a society that promotes male authority and female submission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="admonition note"&gt;
&lt;p class="admonition-title"&gt;Aside&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third definition also fits into past pieces by Piper and hosted on Desiring God such as &lt;a href="https://www.desiringgod.org/interviews/should-women-be-police-officers"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; that says all women should avoid all interactions with men that are both personal and directive. The piece is relatively recent (eight years) and it certainly fits into the third definition of patriarchy - a society that promotes male authority and female submission. But is that what Kevin is advocating for as a biblical vision? I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So given the lack of an alternate definition, the language about recapturing the past, and the rest of the article, I believe the phrase “something like the patriarchy” does not mean “a new and heavily modified version of the patriarchy without so many objectionable parts.” Instead, I believe Kevin means “the concept of patriarchy as it has historically existed, whatever we happen to call it.” Please let me know in the comments if I’m misreading Kevin here; this point is pretty fundamental to get right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="recap"&gt;Recap&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the the stage is set. If I’ve got this right, Kevin’s position is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The rule of men across society (and the submission of women) reflects innate gender differences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No form of complementarianism is sustainable without patriarchy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The historical expression of patriarchy does not reflect significant oppression or prejudice.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The above claims align with the best hermeneutical interpretations of the Bible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, those are certainly bold and audacious claims. I’ll pick this up next time looking at Kevin’s argumentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="footnote"&gt;
&lt;hr/&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:barr"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See my discussion later in this article of historian &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/bethallisonbarr"&gt;Beth Barr’s&lt;/a&gt; definition of patriarchy, and why I think this option is the best one. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:barr" title="Jump back to footnote 1 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:gender"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure whether Kevin meant “a lost vision of (sexual differentiation) and order” or “a lost vision of sexual (differentiation and order)” here. I’m pretty sure he envisions the latter, though, because throughout the article, gender differentiation at a societal level comes up - the discussion of matriarchies, the idea of centuries of men and women occupying different roles in the world reflecting innate differences, the reference to cities and schools. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:gender" title="Jump back to footnote 2 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li id="fn:defend"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were going to try and defend some version of the patriarchy, for example, I might consider arguing that in typical situations, people are better off if well-qualified men lead – with special attention given to how to protect against abuse and poor leadership. It’s still a difficult and unpopular argument, but at least it can acknowledge a lot of historical wrongdoing and differentiate itself from simply repeating the past. &lt;a class="footnote-backref" href="#fnref:defend" title="Jump back to footnote 3 in the text"&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><category term="Reviews"></category><category term="DeYoung"></category><category term="Patriarchy"></category></entry></feed>